A Guide to the Thomas and Daniel Higginbotham and Company (Lynchburg, Va.) Journals and Ledgers, 1815-1827
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Thomas and Daniel Higginbotham and Company (Lynchburg, Va.) Journals and Ledgers, 1815-1827
Library of Virginia
1105957, 1105958, 1105959, 1105964, 1105967, 1105969, 1105971, 1105975, 1105982, 1105985, 1105990, and 1106006
12 vol. (4251 p.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Amherst County.
Historical Information
Thomas and Daniel Higginbotham and Company was part of a chain of mercantile businesses owned by Thomas, Daniel and David Higginbotham. The three were brothers from Amherst County who were prominent mercantilists in early nineteenth century Virginia. Either together or with other mercantilists, the Higginbotham brothers operated general stores in New Glasgow, Amherst, Lynchburg, Richmond and other localities in Virginia.
Scope and Content
Thomas and Daniel Higginbotham and Company Journals and Ledgers, 1815-1827, consist of five journals and seven ledgers. They record the company's activities in Lynchburg.
Journals A, B, D, E, and G, 1815-1821, are daybooks that record transactions chronologically on a daily basis. Each entry include the page number of the customer's individual account found in corresponding ledgers A, B, and G found in this collection. Ledger E is missing. Information found in each journal entry includes name of customer, items purchased, and the amount owed and paid. Merchandise sold included paper, clothing, knives, spices, dishes, and tools.
Ledgers A-D and F-H, 1816-1821, record the accounts of individual customers. Each entry includes the page number found in corresponding journals, A, B, D, and G where the customer's specific transactions can be found. Journals C, F, and H are missing. Although one ledger says Ledger E on the spine, it is actually Ledger C. Each account lists transactions in chronological order and the amount owed and paid. Also records store's controlling accounts including merchandise account, cash account, postage account, etc.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Related materials may be found in Accession 21597 and 21717 which include the following: Thomas and Daniel Higginbotham and Company (Richmond, Va.) Business Records, Daniel and David Higginbotham and Company Business Records, John and Richard Shelton Ellis Business Records, Richard Shelton Ellis Business Records, Archibald Robertson and Company Business Records, Samuel Read and Company Business Records, John James London Records, Thomas Higginbotham Records, and Soldier's Joy Plantation Records.
Access Terms
Corporate Name
Thomas and Daniel Higginbotham and Company (Lynchburg, Va.)
Subject Terms
Consumer goods--Virginia--Lynchburg.; Dry-goods--Virginia--Lynchburg.; General stores--Virginia--Lynchburg.
Geographic Terms
Amherst County (Va.)--History--19th century.; Lynchburg (Va.)--History--19th century.
Record Type
Business records--Virginia--Lynchburg.; Daybooks--Virginia--Lynchburg.; Journals (accounts)--Virginia--Lynchburg.; Ledgers (account books)--Virginia--Lynchburg.; Local government records--Virginia--Lynchburg.
Occupation Terms
Merchants--Virginia--Lynchburg.
Added Entries - Personal Names
Higginbotham, Daniel. 1781-1845.; Higginbotham, Thomas. 1769-1835.
Contents List
- Journal A, 1815-1816, 1105957
- Ledger A, 1815-1816, 1105969
- Journal B, 1816-1817, 1105959
- Ledger B, 1816-1817, 1105967
- Ledger C, 1817-1818, 1105982
- Journal D, 1818-1819, 1106006
- Ledger D, 1818-1819, 1105985
- Journal E, 1819-1820, 1105958
- Ledger F, 1820-1821, 1105990
- Journal G, 1821-1822, 1105964
- Ledger G, 1821-1822, 1105971
- Ledger H, 1822-1827, 1105975